Brittany Bugg

brittanylauren08@gmail.com | (801) 960-5463

PROFILE

Driven and passionate recent graduate with an abundance of knowledge and experience in the fields of biology, botany, and zoology pursuing an opportunity to become a laboratory instructor for biology labs at Utah Valley University.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science, Botany (Awaiting approval from graduation office, 2022)

- GPA: 3.26
- Utah Valley University, Orem, UT

Bachelor of Science, Biology (2017)

Utah Valley University, Orem, UT

AWARDS

Dean's List, Spring 2022

• GPA: 4.0

Dean's List, Fall 2021

GPA: 4.0

FUNDING

SAC Grant (\$256), Utah Valley University (February 2022)

- Group project to fund research on community assembly of fungi on Utah's trees URSCA Grant (\$2,000), Utah Valley University (December 2021)
- Individual project to fund research on the niche profiles of Utah's carnivorous plants QUICK Grant (\$2,500), Utah Valley University (April 2015)
 - Written and funded for Dr. Kristine Doty-Yells, College of Humanities and Social Sciences, Utah Valley University
 - Funds for research on comparing the patterns of behavior toward early versus on-time return missionaries

STEM Classroom Grant (\$1,500), State of Utah (April 2015)

- Written and funded for Melanie Oviatt (5th grade teacher, Alpine School District)
- Funds for tablets in the Google Chromebooks for students in the classroom

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Utah's Greenest Meateater: Mapping the Home of Utah's only Carnivorous Plant

 Purpose: Establish niche habitat profiles to further conservation efforts and better understand their role in Utah's habitats

Phylogenetic Patterns and Bioclimatic Correlations of Genome Size Variation in Leucaena

 Purpose: Illustrate connections between phylogenetic patterns and bioclimatic correlations to genome size of various species in genus of *Leucaena*

Community Assembly of Wood Decomposing Fungi on Utah's Dominant Tree Species

 Purpose: Track the order of arrival in community assembly of wood-decomposing fungi on Utah's two most dominant tree species *Populus tremuloides* and *Juniperus* osteosperma and its effect on ecosystem processes

PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS

2022 **Bugg B.L.**, Peterson Z., Shaver T., and Rotter, M.C. Utah's Greenest Meateater: Mapping the Home of Utah's only Carnivorous Plant.

Presented at:

- UCUR (poster presentation)
- NCUR (poster and oral presentation)
- Utah Valley University Showcase (poster and oral presentation)

VOLUNTEER/SERVICE EXPERIENCE

Wildlife Rehabilitation Volunteer – Great Basin Wildlife Rescue, Mapleton, UT (April 2017 to Present)

- Assist in rehabilitation of injured wildlife
- General maintenance of aviaries/enclosures
- Dosing/distributing medications to treat animals during convalescence
- Plan and prepare feeding/cleaning/care schedules for animals and ensure all basic needs are met in rehabilitation process
- Train birds of prey declared non-releasable due to injuries/disabilities for community education programs

Owl Expert – Sundance Mountain Resort, Provo, UT

(December 2016 to Present)

- Give presentations on facts, the roles, and importance of owls in the world
- Present non-releasable owls to give others the chance to observe owls in close proximity
- Answer questions about owls and assist in guided snowshoe hikes to call for local owls

Volunteer Church Service – Sofia, Bulgaria

(2010 to 2011)

• Taught free English classes to native Bulgarians

- Participated in community service projects
- Volunteered at local non-profits such as orphanages

WORK EXPERIENCE

Researcher, Utah Valley University

(January 2022 to June 2022)

- Used imageJ software to count and measure herbarium specimens found in Utah
- Analyzed the data and assisted in building figures with said data
- Produced posters and presentations illustrating the significance of data collected
- Attempted to find specimens in Utah currently (which is proving quite difficult)

Pharmacy Technician, Macey's Pharmacy

(May 2012 to Present)

- Maintained inventory process and stocked orders
- Assisted pharmacist in any available capacity, including but not limited to customer service, interfacing with medical staff and/or insurance companies, compounding medications to precise dosages for counter dispensation, and medical billing
- Memorized state laws and regulations to better resolve third-party issues such as doctor prior authorizations and insurance claims and ensure compliance with state and federal mandates

Pharmacy Internal Auditor, Associated Retail Operations

(February 2014 to December 2016)

- Conducted internal audits to inspect 10 company pharmacies to meet all company standards for workflow, recordkeeping, and cleanliness
- Ensured proper management of pharmaceutical inventories
- Reviewed records for compliance with all federal, state, and third-party regulations

Environmental Educator (Internship), Tracy Aviary

(May 2015 to August 2015)

- Planned, developed materials, and facilitated interactive experiences, tours, scout workshops, and other educational programs for visitors at Tracy Aviary
- Interpreted and presented a comprehensive range of watershed ecology topics to a variety of audiences
- Developed, presented, and implemented a capstone internship project

SKILLS

Laboratory Experience

- Hundreds of hours spent in lab courses in the subjects of biology, chemistry, physics, botany, zoology, microbiology, and mycology
- Specific techniques include DNA extraction, PCR (preparation and analysis), plating, etc.

Public Speaking

- Numerous presentations given to a range of audiences, from private events to public school demonstrations
- Presentations delivered in English and Bulgarian

Group Work

 Collaborated with many fellow students, coworkers, and professors on a multitude of projects

Grant Writing

- Written numerous grant
- Majority have been funded

Computer Skills

- Proficient in Microsoft Office
- "R" Data Analysis Programming

Lesson Planning

- Produced lessons during religious service mission to teach English and/or religion
- Wrote lesson plans for scout groups to earn merit badges during internship
- Wrote lesson plans for children attending summer day camps during internship

Botany Skills

- Proficient in plant identification by using dichotomous keys, most notably in Utah's native plant species
- Collecting and preserving specimens for use in an herbarium
- Experience in plant care/horticulture including garden planning and care, indoor plant care, and plant propagation

Zoology Skills

- Proficient in identification of Utah's native birds by appearance and sound
- Experience in mammal tracking in the field and identification
- Extensive experience in the care and rehabilitation of mammals and birds, specifically birds of prey
- Trained a variety of non-releasable birds of prey for handling during educational programs

Ecology Skills

- Experience in quadrat, transect, and plot techniques used in the field
- Analysis and interpretation of collected data for specimens observed in the field

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

- Utah County Birders Association (as of July 2016)
- Great Basin Wildlife Rescue, Member of the Board of Directors (as of September 2017)

REFERENCES

- Michael Rotter, PhD, Assistant Professor, Department of Biology, Utah Valley University in Orem, UT. Email: MRotter@uvu.edu, Phone: (231) 250-3061
- Stephanie Hughes PharmD, Staff Pharmacist, Macey's Pharmacy in Provo, UT. Email: stephanie.hughes@afstores.com, Phone: (801) 472-3193
- Patti Richards, Director of Great Basin Wildlife Rescue in Mapleton, UT. Email: greatbasinrehab@yahoo.com, Phone: (801) 310-0186